Guide to the Collection of African Colonial Collectible Sticker Albums TAM.776
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Collection of African Colonial Collectible Sticker Albums
circa 1920-1975, undated
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
TAM.776
2.0 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box, 1 half manuscript box, 1 flat box and 2 oversize flat folders
The materials in this collection are primarily albums to hold collectible stickers and stamps. Some of the albums were made by corporations as promotional and educational tools to market their products. The albums all depict life, people, and landscapes of European colonies in Africa, with the bulk of albums focused on the Democratic Republic of Congo (formerly known as the Belgian Congo).
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 17 albums of trading cards and stamps from the 1920s through the 1970s. The bulk of these albums focus on life in the Belgian Congo (later known as the Democratic Republic of Congo), Rhodesia, and other European colonies in Africa. The albums and cards were produced by corporations such as Players Tobacco, Astra Confectioners, and a variety of chocolatiers. The stamps were packaged with their products and used for marketing and promotional purposes. The bulk of the albums in this collection were intended for children. This collection illustrates the intersection of colonialism and advertising, and how colonial life was portrayed to the people living on the mainland.
The collection also includes an undated poster for a student protest of colonialism, a promotional poster about rubber plantations in the Belgian Congo, and three prints illustrating life in the colonies of Kenya and Rhodesia.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
There is no documentation concerning the acquisition of these materials. The accession number associated with this collection is 2019.014.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Cigarette cards.; sticker books; Congo (Democratic Republic); Imperialism.; Colonies -- Africa
- Military Uniforms of the British Empire Overseas, circa 1930-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Album Congo, circa 1930-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Afrika, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Belgisch Congo Geschiedenis en Ontwikkeling, circa 1920-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Africa Albums, 1960s, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- People of the World Albums, 1940-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- People of the World Albums, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Voyage de Sa Majesté le Roi Baudoin Premier au Congo Belge en 1955, circa 1955, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Belgisch Congo Belge Albums, 1940s, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Cosmorama de Africa, 1950-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Deutsche Kolonien, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Notre Congo Album, 1948 (Box Shared Tamiment 054, Folder 1)
- African Colonial Prints and Poster, 1940-1960, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 048, Folder 11)
- Belgisch Kong Poster, circa 1945, undated (Folder 12 Right)